hey what's up everybody thanks for
listening to The Grow Your Life podcast
I'm so excited that you're here thanks
for being with me
today we're going to talk about how you
can use chat CPT to boost your mental
wellness and I had a short walk and talk
on my social media this week where I
went over this but I actually want to
break down a demo for you how this all
works and so if you're able to watch
this episode on YouTube look up the
title on YouTube and you'll be able to
actually find the video of it as I go
through this now we're using gpt4 which
right now uh has a little bit of a cap
on it but we have a way around that cap
with an app called po dot AI uh whoops
not po dot AI but if I type in po AI
we'll be able to find it and they're
running the GPT
um engine as well which is awesome so
either way we'll be able to demonstrate
how you can use chat CPT particularly
the gpt4 engine that just came out
because it's so much more powerful than
GPT 3.5 especially at reasoning and
conciseness and that's very key when it
comes to mental health and mental
Wellness type of scenarios okay so what
I do is I love using the microphone and
so one thing that you're going to want
to do is download go to type in chat GPT
voice into Google and if you're using
Google Chrome and click on voice control
for chat GPT okay
so this gives you a little microphone
button that you can use in chat GPT if
you're using your cell phone I love the
microphone function that's built into
the iPhone their ability to uh tell what
I'm saying and interpret my language and
things like that it's really really
great really intuitive so but voice
control works with the computer
otherwise most your phones have voice to
text that you can use on your cell phone
works either way again you're going to
want to make sure that you're using the
gpt4 model which is capped right now it
just came out this week uh gbg 3.5 can
also work you just might not get as good
of results out of it okay so we can see
right here as I'm talking into the
screen it is pulling up the words that
I'm saying and it's actually
transcribing them right into chat GPT if
you're watching the video you can see
the video the words that I'm saying are
actually appearing on the screen right
here okay I'm going to cancel that
because I don't want to submit the
message so here's what I do I start by
dialoguing
a brain dump
of what I'm going through and feeling
and experiencing with no edits
no nothing and so I'm actually going to
walk you through me doing this over
something that came up today for me
something that hopefully I overcome and
this is going to be super vulnerable and
and possibly exposing of my personality
to you just a little bit
um I may in fact be risking my
reputation on a very deep level by
walking you through this with me
so stay tuned
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
describe a chat GPT what was actually
going on and we're going to actually
walk through the process
so I was in a Facebook group and it was
a group around people that were talking
about their mental health issues and
therapy and I ended up sharing some
advice somebody was asking a question
about something and I shared some advice
and somebody asked me
what what part of me
felt the need to give that person advice
when they shared
immediately I got triggered
I shut down
I felt like they were questioning me I
felt attacked I felt like I was bad
for giving advice in this setting
that I should have just kept my mouth
shut
and instead I responded I said no no
thanks I'm good and then I said
well in fact it was the part of me
that could just do whatever I want
and then I ended up getting banned from
the group because they felt like that
response was not very kind and
I've had this happen before multiple
times inside Facebook groups where I've
gotten banned because I've actually just
said what I was thinking when I was
feeling and truthfully that's what it
was apparently this group was not a safe
space to even share advice when somebody
was sharing and I
didn't know that and then when somebody
was questioning me if I was okay at
doing this
I was triggered and I responded in a
certain way
new paragraph
can you help me work through this
question mark
[Music]
and here's the output it sounds like
you've had a challenging experience with
Facebook groups and it's understandable
that you may feel triggered or attacked
in a certain situation here are some
steps to work through it reflecting your
feelings take some time to think about
what you felt you felt triggered and
attacked was it the tone the phrasing
the content of the comment
consider the context and online
discussions it's essential to be aware
of group guidelines and tone some groups
have strict rules about giving advice
while there's a more open to that
practice self-compassion remind yourself
that everyone makes mistakes and it's
okay to feel hurt and triggered try to
be kind to yourself and develop
assertive communication style so what I
did was I actually did assert myself
but it was a little more on the
aggressive side
and
so it says I apologize if I overstepped
or if it wasn't helpful yeah good advice
so now here's where I would use chat GPT
right here
act as if you are a parts work therapist
or an internal family systems therapist
and write a script
to help me integrate these parts of me
that still feel like I'm a bad boy or a
bad person because I got ostracized and
kicked out and questioned and criticized
by members of the group
[Music]
because that's what I was feeling as an
AI language model I'm not a licensed
therapist but I can attempt to guide you
through an ifs inspired exercise please
remember this not a substitute for
professional therapy and so this is
where we end up going with this here's a
script to help you integrate the part it
feels like a bad person due to the
experiences you've had in the group
and yes this is this is something that
I've worked through and dealt with
find a quiet space to focus take a few
deep breaths imagine you're sitting in
the room with different parts of
yourself
you might picture the younger version of
yourself as characters
identify the part that feels like a bad
boy or is ostracized or criticized or
questioned by the group invite this part
to sit with you as you listen practice
compassion and understanding okay so I'm
going to pause it right here
please write a script that scripts out
the exact conversation between these
parts of me and myself
in the script U represents core self a
part A represents the part feeling like
a bad person
the goal of this conversations promote
understanding integration and healing
thank you for joining me I want to hear
about your thoughts and understand why
you feel like a bad person when you're
criticized or questioned in a group I
feel hurt and rejected by people that
criticize us or question our intentions
makes me feel like I'm not good enough
or that we've done something wrong it's
like we're being punished for trying to
help or express ourselves
I hear that you're feeling hurt or
rejected when you experience those
situations it sounds like you're trying
to protect us from feeling this way I
think I need reassurance that I'm not a
bad person just because we make mistakes
or our intentions are misunderstood by
others
it's hard for me to accept that not
everyone is always willing to approve of
me
I understand this is challenging
that we can't please everybody and it's
okay to make mistakes and I want to
reassure you that making mistakes
being understood doesn't make us a bad
person see this is actually helping me
right now
I like that but I just don't like
feeling like we're on the outside always
being judged and ostracized I need to
know that we have worth and value we
have worth in value no matter what
others think
let's find ways to remind ourselves that
when we Face criticism and rejection
let's have self-compassion that sounds
good maybe we can start focusing on
building a support group of people who
understand and appreciate us for who we
are so we don't feel so alone when the
going gets tough that's a great idea
okay but in that right now I'm feeling
like
and this is the this is the big part of
it okay
I'm feeling like
there's still some sort of underlying
issue going on here
and so here's what I want to ask I want
I want it to
ask me a series of questions as if
you're a therapist to help us get to the
root issue and identify a repressed deep
memory about the issue that we're
dealing with
and this is where things get fun
can you recall a specific moment or
incident in your past where you felt
similarly
criticized or ostracized
I can think of a couple moments where I
felt this way similarly uh one was where
I was DJing and I had a guy attack me
because I was successfully DJing better
than him
and he threatened to kill me
wow
I had forgotten all about that
I had another situation where
I had great input to give to a group for
a client that I was working with and
they shut me down and said that I was
operating out of demons and doing
horrible things
so these were when I was an adult
what emotions you remember feeling
during those events I felt terrified and
scared I literally felt powerless
and they made me think that if I don't
act right and always do the right things
I will get hurt and people will come
after me
were there any significant people in
your life at the time who might have
contributed to or reinforced these
feelings absolutely
um they were generally leaders they were
leaders of groups who were in charge of
a group of people who basically told
entire friend groups to not be friends
with me because I didn't
fit into the version of their behavior
that they demanded that I beat
wow
this is me just literally verbalizing
out all this as I'm reading it
how have these past experiences
influence your current beliefs about
yourself interactions with others well
they've caused me to be cautious and to
watch what I say but I have moments
where I feel excited and I want to share
things and then I get slapped in the
face
just like I did in the Facebook group
for actually acting on some of those
thoughts that I have when I feel
confident
okay
foreign
are there any patterns in your
relationship interactions with others
that might be connected to a past
experience or belief
that you formed yeah absolutely is that
I just I I'm not
safe to be confident
that when I act confidently
that bad things happen and I need to
protect myself from attackers from
people shutting me down ultimately not
just attacking me but shutting me down
can you think of any positive
experiences or accomplishments in your
life by the way
this is an area that I've been working
through for almost the last week
can you think of any positive
experiences in your life
that might challenge these beliefs about
being a bad person or unworthy
absolutely I have so many clients that
think that we're absolutely incredible
we're helping them they love when I
share advice sometimes I'm just not as
prudent about when to open my mouth how
do you feel in situations where you
criticized or questioned what changes
would you like to make well what I would
like to do is a not be afraid to open my
mouth and say the things that I'm
thinking
um even if it upsets people I also would
like to not be triggered and completely
shut down or get reactive when somebody
questions if I'm good or bad or not
okay so I'm going to submit that as well
it sounds like you've had some
challenging experiences being threatened
and ostracized by others particularly in
situations that contribute to expressing
yourself
acknowledge and validate your emotions
this is a hundred percent again I know
some of you are watching this like whoa
did he make all this up no it's actual
stuff that I'm dealing with that I've
dealt with and I'm being vulnerable
enough to show you and share this with
you and actually walk you through how I
use this stuff
acknowledge your emotions reframe the
beliefs identify any negative beliefs
that you formed
develop coping strategies set boundaries
build a support group practice
self-compassion
it's great that you identify these
patterns
develop assertiveness skills
okay so obviously being a supportive
environment is great
I'm going to copy these strategies that
it's giving me and I'm gonna say can you
please map out for me in detail
how I can do the following
as it relates to the above
reframing your beliefs identify the
negative beliefs write them down
do you have about yourself and your
interactions for example I'm not safe to
be confident or when I act confidently
bad things happen challenge these
beliefs these beliefs fund evidence in
your life that contradicts it okay uh
can you write down in your opinion
20 possible
negative
beliefs as they relate to the above
then can you help me
challenge these
and finally help me
reframe them
coping strategies listen your triggers
brainstorm coping strategies deep
breathing exercises positive
affirmations reaching out to a trusted
friend or support group
practicing self-compassion it's so key
for me self-compassion is my big one
practice using them when faced with a
trigger in a future situation a Justice
strategy that's most effective in
combination learn about assertiveness
learn to be assertive attend workshops
and assertiveness I'm probably going to
stop at generating I wanted to see what
it comes up with okay so we already used
all the GPT 4 info
see if I can copy this into here real
quick
let's see if this generates anything for
us
now see it looks like it's way too much
text
way too much text okay
so we have enough data in here but let's
let's feed um gpt3 and see what it says
I'm not good enough I'm a bad person
when I say thing I always say the wrong
things I don't deserve to be heard I'm
always going to be criticized I can't
trust myself to speak up people always
judge and reject me identify the
evidence that contradicts with I've
for example I've received feedback from
others I have skills and talents that
are valuable consider alternative
explanations maybe they're having a bad
day perhaps I don't need to explain
myself I don't explain myself well
enough perhaps I don't need to explain
myself
I've received many compliments
I'm good enough and have valuable
qualities to offer I'm a good person who
makes mistakes the ability to
communicate effectively and say the
right thing I deserve to be heard and
have my opinions considered criticism is
an opportunity for growth and learning I
trust myself to speak up and express
myself in a respectful way
okay
so let's take some of this right here
's what I'm going to do is we're just
going to take this we're going to
identify it
we're going to take
just these core
um keys
let's bring those into po
or
okay message send failed so it's too
many too many characters for po that's
okay
and not as progress you make you folks
okay awesome so now we've fed this info
into Poe
so now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to go back through and I'm going to ask
a couple of questions
act as if you are a psychology Professor
teaching a college level class and
identifying the root cause of mental
health issues that relate to the above
topic how would you walk your students
through this process hello we'll be
discussing the process of identifying
root cause mental health issues related
to experiences of criticism ostracism
and feeling of unworthiness
gather information about the
individual's history identify patterns
explore their underlying beliefs
consider the role of cognitive
distortions that's a good one
help me to understand this
okay so I gotta wait till it's done
printing this out
but you see how like chat GPT can help
you really dive deep into
certain issues that you're feeling by
letting it ask you certain questions
and letting it
continue along the certain path with you
cognitive distortions are ways that the
brain convinces us of something that's
not necessarily true
these are inaccurate thoughts let's take
a look all or nothing thinking black and
white terms no middle ground for example
individuals might believe that if they
aren't perfect they're a complete
failure I've dealt with that
it's kind of thinking can lead to
unworthiness over generalization a
single negative event applies broadly
if somebody's rejection a social
situation could conclude that they're
going to be rejected and fundamentally
unlikable
I've dealt with that as well
okay
so let's try this right here
act as if you're doing Shadow work with
me and ask me questions to help me
identify my shadow
evaluate the evidence become aware of
the distorted thought ask yourself
practice cognitive restructuring to help
replace distorted Thoughts with more
balanced ones by addressing these
distortions that can break free from
cycles and negative patterns okay
process of exploring and integrating the
unconscious aspects
the shadow consists of repressed its own
what are some traits or behaviors and
others that you find particularly
irritating or upsetting
type it into here
and we'll do the same thing
act as if we're doing Shadow work and
ask me five questions to help me
identify my shadow
can you recall any instances where
you've exhibited these same traits and
behaviors this is good
so what I found is that in other people
um
I was particularly irritated and upset
by being ostracized or cast out that
people wouldn't listen to me or even
have any
um
willingness to hear me out
yes I have it when I prejudge somebody
strongly I've completely cut them off
out of my life and they've gotten very
angry with me and actually come after me
when I've tried to keep myself safe
there are aspects that you feel ashamed
of or try to keep hidden
um I think that I react reactively
sometimes
without thinking I say things
that are out of turn that are like wow
because a lot of people compliment me
for being very articulate I am a public
figure on social media and then
sometimes just out of the blue I can
completely like 180 and have a
completely different personality that's
not fun to be around that shows up but
it happens way less than it used to it
happens in triggering situations
when somebody points out a flaw about me
or criticizes me well
I get upset I get angry
um if it's somebody that I love
my wife like I take it in and I
understand it and I'm accepting of it
but when it's just some random person I
actually get kind of upset about it
which isn't fair to them
what are some personal values that my
self-esteem matters and that my
self-belief matters
I felt envious and jealous of people who
always have self-confidence no matter
who criticizes them and they're
unwavering and don't get triggered by it
I feel like it's been difficult to
express
why I've been so afraid of people coming
after me and attacking me
okay so I'm gonna take this
into chat GPT
I'll answer it
might be related to feelings of
vulnerability fear of rejection
defensive response to criticism you
mentioned that you feel particularly
upset when you're not hurt or cast out
by others defensiveness and reactive
behaviors
okay
inconsistency and self-esteem yep it's
good
in case then I would go back to act as
if you're a parts work therapist or
internal family systems therapist and
write a script
to help me integrate and unblend these
parts of me
take a moment and check in I have
tension in my chest and bit of anxiety
feeling envious and judgmental I think
it's a critical part let's see over here
therapist first I'd like you to find a
comfortable place
take a few
deep slow breaths
identify the part of you that feels
particularly present or active right now
[Music]
okay
so you could answer some of those
questions
particularly I feel a part that is
afraid of being rejected
once
to just be seen or do whatever it wants
notice the sensation you're feeling now
imagine that you can communicate with it
what specific situations have you
triggered that how did you cope with it
well I shut down I cut everybody out of
my life
because being seen mean to you
people willing to acknowledge me
so I've had situations where people
criticized me that I wasn't good enough
that I was a bad person that should just
be silent that I should just shut up
that I'm a terrible person for speaking
up and I cope by just running away
cutting them out of my life and ignoring
it all
when it's being seen mean to you why is
it important
what do you need to feel
is that I can make mistakes and I'm not
going to be beat up or punished for it
foreign
experienced a lot of pain and fear
related to criticism or judgment from
others the desire to be seen accepted
without fear of being punished or making
mistakes is very human and an
understandable need let's explore ways
to support and reassure this part of you
first take a moment to validate the pain
that you're having practice
self-compassion everything I pull up
keeps pulling up self-compassion find a
support group of trusted friends develop
healthy boundaries and it's true
and so this is where then I would go to
the affirmations prompt
and I would have it develop a list of
affirmations
I am worthy of love and acceptance no
matter what mistakes I make
I trust myself to make the best decision
for myself and my life I release the
need for validation from others and find
confidence Within Myself I embrace my
unique qualities and talents and share
them with the world
awesome
see what this generates
here are 100 affirmations
I'm worthy of love and respect I embrace
my Perfections and learn from them my
voice matters and I have the right to
express myself I am deserving of
kindness and understanding
see this is deep deeper for me I'm
feeling this a lot more
I release my fear of rejection and
criticism
I'm more
than the judgments and opinions of
others so this is triggering parts of me
reading this
that is inspiring even more areas where
there's a part of me that questions the
truth in these words
like maybe I do deserve to be judged
maybe I do deserve to be criticized
maybe I do deserve to be rejected and so
that's why I would dive deeper I would
start to explore a little bit more
and then start to journal that out and
go through the same process again asking
it okay where did I feel you know come
up with some questions to help me find a
deeper pressed memory for why I feel
like I deserve to be rejected by others
why I deserve to be criticized why I
deserve to be ostracized things like
that okay
and so that's really it is you keep
looping through and eventually you'll
get to a point where you're kind of
exhausted and that's where you take a
break and you stop doing it and I only
do it for about 30 minutes we've been
doing it for about 30 minutes now
because that's really kind of the limit
of this is very intense level of self
sort of self therapy
but it's not a replacement for therapy
but it is a way to really kind of dive
deep with yourself and if you go five
ten layers deep with this like if I read
through these affirmations this is kind
of a big one for me
what I'm looking for is I'm looking for
affirmations that trigger
disbelief in me right don't believe the
affirmation and what that is is that is
identifying another sort of part of me
that is
actually reacting in the situation
because it has a hard time believing
that I am compassionate that I deserve
to have a life filled with joy that I'm
a kind and loving person
and that shows up in these situations
where I get criticized and so then we go
back through and we we figure out okay
where did this come from
where was the root cause of this in fact
let's just let's just try this one I'm
gonna go one layer deep with this again
so oftentimes I feel like I don't
deserve
any of those affirmations that are
written there that none of those are
true that I deserve to be criticized
that I deserve to be ostracized that I'm
not worthy of love and acceptance
that I'm not capable of handling
challenges
that
I don't deserve to have supportive
people around me
and this really drives me
in a big way to sort of fight and defend
myself against others
I'm going to have I'm having to use
these two windows here
just because it's uh
gbt 3.5 and gpt4
again you'll notice the gbt4 outputs are
a lot better
consider the source of the negative
beliefs and so this is where I would go
back and I would say
repressed memory questions
when did you first start feeling this
way about yourself
past experience particularly with
rejection
if you felt a similar way in the past if
so how did you overcome it
I'll tell you where I'm actually going
with this is even deeper
because now I'm identifying childhood
memories
where you felt criticized judged or
unworthy
well growing up
my mom always told me that I was not
worthy of
life and that she had thought about
aborting me
and I had a moment where I wanted to
learn to play the piano and I had
friends that didn't like me because I
played the piano and when I told people
I was homeschooled they told me that I
was weird it wasn't worthy to be around
them
how'd your family members respond to
your mistakes or shortcomings I was
verbally abused constantly they were
always critical of everything I did
what kind of message did you receive
about your self-worth that my self-worth
was directly attached to me doing
exactly what other people say and
obeying other people at all times and
never deviating from that
were they significant life events or
relationships that may have contributed
to the feelings of unworthiness or
self-doubt well I definitely can look at
oh the when playing the piano was a big
one because it was such a big part of my
life that I wanted to receive acceptance
from people by showing a skill set
and I instead got rejected as a Showboat
and lost almost all my friends
anything of any patterns or themes that
relate to your self-worth
and current struggle of self-worth yeah
that that I felt like I was doing
something great and good
and other people got angry at me for
doing it
the specific people in your life that
have a strong impact on your self-image
yeah my mom and my friends did
what role do perfectionism and high
expectations play in feelings of
unworthiness Well yeah if I do
everything perfect then I deserve for
people to like me
but that's just not true
and how do your feelings of unworthiness
or self-doubt affect your relationships
with others
well I end up being cautious in what I
say how I live
what I talk about
and who I talk to
[Music]
so I'm going to take this right here
let me copy that into here
thank you for sharing
because you face numerous challenges
including verbal abuse lack of support
and unmet expectations from others so
understandable they've shaped your
beliefs in self-worth as you continue to
work on these here's some strategies
recognize yourself whether it's inherent
not dependent on external factors you're
worth as a person is not determined by
your ability to please others your
accomplishments even as I read that
there's a part of me that doesn't feel
like that's true
a little bit
prior to self-compassion be kind of
compassionate to yourself reframe your
past experiences as you reflect on the
challenges you faced
try to identify the Silver Lining and
growth opportunities or Lessons Learned
this can help you develop more balanced
resilient
effective
hmm
it's definitely getting triggering for
me just a little bit reading some of
this
and so this is probably where I want to
stop
I just want to type in once more
act as if you're a parts work therapist
internal family systems
let's take a moment and identify Parts
either feel unworthy and self-doubt can
you identify them yes the root and past
experiences of rejection and criticism
yes I think there's parts of me that
feel creative and talented and that have
achieved success but they get
overshadowed by self-doubt and feelings
of unworthiness that's so true
let's see what gbt4 says
as a parts worker internal family
systems therapist my goal would be to
help you identify and understand
integrate different parts of yourself
that may be contributing to your
feelings one worthiness yourself doubt
the following script can be used
as a guide to help you explore let's
Focus your attention inward see if I can
identifying parts that might be
contributing to feelings of unworthiness
and self-doubt
again this is way deeper for me
than where I'm willing to go right now
but it's spot on
it's spot on I'm gonna see what kind of
affirmations it comes up with
I'm worthy of love and acceptance and
deserve to be treated with kindness and
respect my self-worth it's not dependent
on the opinions of others yeah those
those are definitely speaking to
something in there that is
getting stirred up as I say these things
I deserve forgiveness and Second Chances
yeah
wow
cool and so that's part of the journey
that's part of the Journey of your
mental health
and
if you've ever worked as a professional
therapist you'll know that they kind of
walk you through certain levels of this
this is a way that you can sort of
rotate between these different commands
these different prompts and sort of sit
with yourself for as long as you feel
comfortable again for me like I hit my
point where I feel uncomfortable now and
that's where I like if I feel like I'm
shutting down I'm like okay I gotta go
do something else I'm not gonna push
further That's my kind of limiting point
and so I'll usually just do like one
session of this
a day
like this that I just walked you through
and I've found great Breakthrough by
doing it uh to supplement my times that
I have with a therapist I still work
with a professional therapist to help me
work through a number of these different
things but this is a great
uh starting place and a great place to
do in your own time to help you grow
learn new things
try out some new things
and just see what happens all right
great life everybody and we'll talk soon
have a good one